Register of the Henryk Jabłoński papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Henryk Jabłoński papers
1936-1996
93060
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, and printed matter relating to governmental administration in Poland, Polish foreign relations, and the Polish educational system.
Jabłoński, Henryk.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1993.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Henryk Jabłoński (1909-2003) was trained as a historian and became an important Polish politician in the People's Republic of Poland, serving as the Minister of Education from 1965 to 1972 and as the President (Chairman of the Council of State) from 1972 to 1985. He joined the Polish Socialist Party (Polska Partia Socjalistyczna) before World War II and was then active in the Polish United Workers' Party, serving in the Central Committee throughout the 1950s, 1960s, and 1970s. From 1976 to 1983 he was the head of the Front Jedności Narodu, and from 1983 to 1990 he led the war veterans organization, Związek Bojowników o Wolność i Demokrację.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Henryk Jabłoński papers consist of photocopies and offprints of articles, speeches, government reports, scattered correspondence, and other writings. The collection was donated by Jabłoński and arranged in packets according to the political party, person, institution or topic to which the documents relate, creating one subject file, arranged alphabetically. The two largest groupings are in Rada Państwa and Stan wojenny w Polsce (1981-1983). The first contains primarily reports of the activities of the Council of State for most of the years in which Jabłoński was its head (1972-1985), while the second contains documents, primarily composed in the mid-1990s, which formed part of the Tribunal of State process investigating the imposition of martial law in Poland in December 1981. These two groupings are made up of documents written by people other than Jabłoński, although some of his own writings can also be found in them.
In contrast, the remaining folders contain documents composed primarily by Jabłoński, being short historical pieces and addresses he delivered either as an official representing the institution itself or writings on the topic of the subject described in the folder groupings. Except for the Stan wojenny w Polsce (1981-1983), which has been arranged by author's last name, the arrangement within each subject is chronological.
Poland--Politics and government--1945-1980.; Poland--Politics and government--1980-1989.; Poland--Foreign relations--1945-1989.; Education--Poland.; Statesmen--Poland.
- Subject File, 1936-1996
  - Front Jedności Narodu, 1976-1981 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Fundacja dla Uniwersytetu Jagiellońskiego, 1982 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Kotarbiński, Tadeusz, 1958-1987 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    Scope and Contents note
    Offprint of article by Jabłoński appearing in Nauka Polska, no. 1, 1987, and copies of correspondence received by Jabłoński from Kotarbiński, 1958 to 1961 and 1981.
  - Ministerstwo oświaty i szkolnictwa wyższego, 1966-1971 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    Many offprints, chiefly from Życie Szkoły Wyższej; short addresses from the 1960s, primarily in French.
  - Polonia, 1973-1988 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    Chiefly speeches.
  - Polska Akademia Nauk, 1956-1986 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    Chiefly offprints from Nauka Polska.
  - Polska Partia Socjalistyczna, 1992-1996 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Rada Państwa, 1947-1985 (Box-folder 1: 8-13)
    Includes addresses by Jabłoński as the Chairman of the Council of State, as well as summaries of activities of the body for 1972 and 1976 to 1985.
  - Społeczny Komitet Odnowy Zabytków Krakowa, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Stan wojenny w Polsce (1981–1983), Komisja Odpowiedzialności Konstytucynej Sejmu RP, 1980-1996 (Box-folder 2: 2-8)
    Primarily written testimony by experts composed between 1994 and 1996, but some commentary written earlier and extracted from other publications has been included. Arranged alphabetically by author’s last name, with a 16-page chronology of events at the beginning and miscellaneous extracts at the end. Major, composed statements by: Kazimierz Barcikowski, Antoni Czubiński, Jerzy Holzer, Henry Jabłoński, Wojciech Jaruzelski, Krystyna Kersten, Janusz Krupski, Jarema Maciszewski, Adam Michnik, Andrzej Paczkowski, Ronald Reagan (with an excerpt also by Alexander Haig), A. Walicki, Andrzej Werblan, and Marian Zgórniak.
  - Związek Bojowników o Wolność i Demokrację, 1982-1990 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1936-1993 (Box-folder 2: 10-11)